<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A wonderfull prophecye contynuyng tyll the yere of our Lorde, M.D.LX made by the famous and excellente clerke, Master Iohn Caryon, astronomer of the prince electour of Brandenborgh, for a glasse or example to them that understand and are wyse, and for a disdayne and reprofe to them that are folysh ; translated out of Doutch into J[n]glysh by Anthony Scoloker.</title>
            <author>Carion, Johannes, 1499-1537 or 8.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1550</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17966</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4626.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3916</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33151175</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33151175</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28976</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17966)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28976)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1873:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A wonderfull prophecye contynuyng tyll the yere of our Lorde, M.D.LX made by the famous and excellente clerke, Master Iohn Caryon, astronomer of the prince electour of Brandenborgh, for a glasse or example to them that understand and are wyse, and for a disdayne and reprofe to them that are folysh ; translated out of Doutch into J[n]glysh by Anthony Scoloker.</title>
                  <author>Carion, Johannes, 1499-1537 or 8.</author>
                  <author>Scoloker, Anthony, fl. 1548.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Anthony Scoloker and Wyllyam Seres, Dwelling in the Sauoyrẽtes Wythout Templebarre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[ca. 1550]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: fragment, all after p. [12] lacking; remainder cropped, stained, torn, and tightly bound. Best copy available for photographing.</note>
                  <note>"Cum Gratia ex priuilegio ad Jmpr[--]."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: John Rylands University Library of Manchester.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:28976:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 132 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:28976:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 132 -->
            <p>A wonder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full Prophecye contynuyng tyll the yere of our Lorde. M.D.LX. Made by the Famous and excellente Clerke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Maſter Iohn Caryon. Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomer of the prince Electour of Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denborgh. For a glaſſe or example to them that vnderſtand and are wyſe: and for a diſday<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne and reprofe to them that are folyſh.</p>
            <p>¶ Tranſlated out of Doutch into I<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glyſh by Anthony Scoloker.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>IMPRINTED</hi> At London / by Anthony Scoloker and Wyllyam Seres Dwelling in the Sauoyre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. Wythout Tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple barre.</p>
            <p>Cum Gratia et priuilegio ad Imp<gap reason="illegible" extent="8 letters">
                  <desc>〈8 letters〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28976:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 133 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:28976:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 133 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:28976:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 134 -->
            <head>To the reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Aſter Iohn Cario<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth / that he hath been a long ſeaſon in mynde to ſet furth ſome good thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g wherby the iuſt a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d good people might be warned, and the wycked feared and threatened. Item Iames Lichtemberger and Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>racelſus haue in lyke caſe much writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after the ſame maner. But verely there was n<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er none y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> at anye tyme hath ſet <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Armes of Emperour / ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs / pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es and Lordes / as Caryon hath. And his prophecy ſhal continue almooſt tyll <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he yeare of our Lorde. m.d.lx. And to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he intent that all men maye the better <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nderſtande or perceyue the ſame / her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fter followeth the expoſytyon of the <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>me Prophetye. For it is not geuen to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uery man to vnderſtand the ſame / but <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto ſuch as haue laboured many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eys or they that haue red much.</p>
            <p>Iohn Cario<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayth furthermore, that <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e time to come will exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or reach no <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rther the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> almoſt tyll the yeare of our <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:28976:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 134 -->
            <head>A wonderfull prophecy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing tyll the yeare of our lorde .m.dlx. Made by the Famous and excellent Clerke, Maſter Iohn Caryon. Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomer of the prince Electour of Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denborgh. For a glaſſe or example to them that vnderſtande and are wyſe: &amp; for a diſdayne and reprofe to them that are folyſh.</head>
            <p>
               <label>The prophecy.</label>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Sorrowfull Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle dyd flye a longe ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, with great diſquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and labour.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The expoſicion.</label>
By this / ye ſhal vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Maximilia<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb facs="tcp:28976:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 135 -->Aboue that Reghenſburgh and the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemians were ſore beaten. And Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milian hym ſelfe ſet firſt vppon them: in the which warre / the prayſeworthye prince Duke Erich of Bru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwyke was wounded to death. Thys Emperoure Maximilian had to do wyth the Byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome and with the worlde. He had warre .viij. yeares agaynſt the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians / he dyed whan he was old .lxiij. yere. He was a louer of ſtories / of all artes and of all learned men.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The prophecye.</label>
He did ſet the neſt of his yong ones vppon a golden ſteple.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The Expoſicion.</label>
That is, Maximilian did bring Phyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyp his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne in the kingdom of Catylle who maried the doughter there. And <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </label> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:28976:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 135 -->
For his lyniall garmentes were with .iij. partes whyte w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ouerth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warte ſtrykes and reade.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The expoſition.</label>
That is Auſtrych which hath a ſhylde, or armes whyte ouerthwarte ſtrypes and reade.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The prophecy.</label>
The Eagle plucked flouredelyce / and marred hyr leaues<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>The expoſition.</label>
That is / Maximilian dyd vexe the frenchmen / as namelye. Anno. M.D. xiiij. Henrye the .viij. king of Inglande went ouer the ſea to Calais with great power for to warre agaynſt the french men. And Maximilian did bring with <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of Braband<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Flaundres
<pb facs="tcp:28976:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 136 -->the frenchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with alſo .iij.c. and .L. of the chefeſt of fraunce which he toke pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners / and the frenchmen left .ix. Ban<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners / and al their prouand and wago<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. In this yere / was Duke he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ry / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> duke of Brou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwykes father / ſhotte to death / at the orte in Fryſelande in the warre of the price of Saxon, in the ende of the ſayde warre.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The prophecy.</label>
And deſtroyed his owne fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers whiche glyttered of blackenes, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d much cattell ſuſteyned damage a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hurt with him.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The expoſicion.</label>
Agayne / It dyd alſo chaunce wonders euell vnto this faythfull prince Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milian. He was taken priſoner at Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in Flandres / in the yere of our lord <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:28976:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 136 -->
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly forſoke him in theſe affayres / and in other warres as in the warres of low doutchla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d / Celtica Fraunce, Zwit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and Venice. And the princes ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyned damage and hurte with him / as the Marquis of Caſtmir / the Duke of browneſwyke / the Earle of Manſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many other whych ſerued hym faythfully.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The prophecye.</label>
He did byte the ſerpent / a<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> was byten of hyr agayne.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Thexpoſition.</label>
By this / I vnderſtand <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the which /  the French kyn<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a ſaying. Ann<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>milian take <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:28976:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 137 -->was he byte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Venetia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> duke of Mylan (in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>federacy promiſed / but lytle kepte) wolde betraye the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour / ſo that he was fayne to wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw himſelfe / but afterwarde he reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed them well therfore.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The prophecy.</label>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd after much diſquietnes / gaue him ſelfe to reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The expoſition.</label>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> he departed from this vale <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nno .m.d and .xix. and was <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>eſtad<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. And it was good <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here euen as it was whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Frederycke hys father <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> death, there <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> kinſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:28976:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 137 -->
               <label>the prophecy.</label>
His yong ones vppon the golden ſteple lyued not longe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The expoſition.</label>
That is to be vnderſtand of king Phil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lip whome the fortune of this worlde hath not muche fauoured / and he came ſkant to the age of .xxx. yeres For he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng abrode a huntinge / did drinke a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den draught by the which he hurted his lyghtes and lyuer / and dyed of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The prophecy.</label>
How beit he left other yong ones.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The expoſition</label>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:28976:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 138 -->
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gary, who, Anno .m.d.xxvi. after tun<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>té and inſurrection of the ruſticalle Soliman the Turkyſh Emperour b<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng come with great power into Ho<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gary, And came by Belgrado /  and th<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſayde good Kyng Lodowyke, being l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> helpleaſe and comfortles of all Chri<gap reason="illegible" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> princes, concluded with hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe to dr<gap reason="illegible" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> towardes y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſayd Turkiſh Emperou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> So it chaunced / that the ſayd Turk<gap reason="illegible" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> did ſet harde vppon the Hongaria<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſlewe Tomorrius, byſſhoppe <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Strigonia, The byſſhop alſo of V<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>radin, with other mo. And after th<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Kyng Lodowyke was ſet amonge<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> horſemen in fleyng and withdrawin<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> backe / was caſt from his horſes bac<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and was troden of the other horſes <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo kylled. Thus miſerably ended th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> noble prynce his lyfe, in the defence <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his owne natyue contreye, ſo that h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it ſemeth. <q xml:lang="lat">Honeſtum bellu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> turpi pace melius.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </label> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:28976:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 138 -->
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rought vp in their youth in great qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>the expoſicion.</label>
By this vnderſtand Charles and Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inand.</p>
            <p>
               <label>the prophecy.</label>
But whan they cam to their eares, they weried their winges.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The expoſition.</label>
As by experience we haue ſene / and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et do daylye ſee / by greate warres as in Fraunce / in Affryke and in the land of Gulyke and other, I holde my peace of the inſufferable diete or holding of a counſell / wherewith the Emp<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>rs mai<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtie hath bene ful ſore burthened / beſydes that the Turke c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſeth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely to haue to do with the king / by rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon wherof although their wi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs were ſtron<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> become feble and weake.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:28976:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 139 -->
               <label>
                  <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </label> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> yalow lyon in the blewe felde.</p>
            <p>
               <label>the expoſition.</label>
That is / the Duke of Gelder. Which came to paſſe whan the Emperour gat Gelder and Gulick and compelled the Duke to make contract with him.</p>
            <p>
               <label>the prophecy.</label>
He ſhall breake out the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents teth / that he ſhall not byte.</p>
            <p>
               <label>the expoſicion.</label>
That cam to paſſe with the citie of My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan / whan Pope clement the .vij. (that ſpirituall man) wolde haue an occaſion to warre, forſoke the Emperour. In the caſtel of the ſayde cytie of Mylan / was Franciſcus Sfortia beſeged. And the ceſarians wanne the cytie, &amp; playde many a prowd and arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t parte, whe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>with they taught the inhabitauntes o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Mylan maners / in vyolatinge of their wyues / doughters and maydens / an<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpoyled them of their goods and riche<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes / and ſo that they were whole and al<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vndone: And were compelled / through famyne and lacke of ſuſtenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / to yeld<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſayed caſtell.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28976:8"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 139 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
